There are moments in time where it's
very smart to be contrarian.
>> Mhm.
>> And there are moments in time where
being consensus is the smartest possible
thing you can do. And I think right now
we're in a moment in time where being
consensus is very right.
You know, and you can really overthink
it and what's the contrarian thing? We
should go do a bunch of hardware stuff
cuz blah blah blah.
And like maybe just buy more AI. You
know what I mean? It's I think people
make these things way too complicated.
>> Oh, yeah, true in every aspect of life,
probably.
A lot, nice to see you. Thanks for
making the time. Appreciate it.
>> Good to see you as always.
>> And I thought we could begin with
something that we were chatting about or
you were explaining before we started
recording, which is
a new phenomenon of sorts. Could you
explain what we were just talking about?
>> Oh, yeah. We were We were just talking
about some of the acquisitions that are
happening in the AI world. We saw that
XAI just got an option to effectively
purchase Cursor, it looks like.
Obviously, Scale was sort of partially
taken by Meta. There've been a variety
of these sort of deals that have been
happening over the last year or two.
And separate from that, we were just
talking about what does that mean for
the AI research community and the AI
community in general? And I think the
most interesting or one of the
interesting things that's happened over
the last year or so is Meta really
started aggressively bidding on AI
talent, which is a very rational
strategy, right? They're going to spend
tens of billions of dollars on compute.
So, it made sense to have a real budget
to go after people.
And normally what happens in tech is a
single company will go public.
And a bunch of people from that company
will be enriched and then a subset of
them will continue to be heads down and
working really hard and focus on their
original mission. And a subset of people
start to get distracted. They may go and
work on passion projects for society.
They may get involved with politics.
They may go start a company. They may
just kind of check out and hang out or
go to the beach uh-huh kind of thing.
And what happened recently is because of
the Meta offers and then all the other
major tech companies having to match
offers for their best researchers,
somewhere between 50 and a few hundred
people effectively had an IPO but as a
class of people. it wasn't like they
were a one company, they were spread
across Silicon Valley, but all of their
pay packages suddenly went up
dramatically and they experienced the
equivalent of an IPO and that's really
unusual. It's kind of the personal IPO.
And the only time in history I can think
of where I've seen it happen before is
in crypto
where a bunch of the really early crypto
holders or founders suddenly as a class
all went effectively public in 20, I
guess 17-ish.
>> Mhm.
>> And then again more recently, but this
is really interesting. It's kind of
under discussed. It It may not have huge
long-term implications, but it does mean
a subset of people will
change what they're focused on, try and
do big science projects to help
humanity, work on
AI for science maybe, maybe some people
will go off and do personal quests or
you know, things like that.
>> Or just quiet quit and do lots of drugs
and chase vices. I mean, there's that
too.
>> Definitely not.
>> In that case, you look around say
Austin, you've got the Dellionaires,
which refers to Dell post-IPO early
employees and so on. But as a class of
people when that happens, I suppose we
don't know how
how large or how long-term the
implications are, but there seem to be
implications and I don't know anyone,
well, I know only a few people who I
would go to as
technical enough and also kind of broad
enough in their awareness and networks
to watch AI and to the extent that
someone can watch it comprehensively, I
would put you in that bucket and you
wrote this week just to talk about some
of the other
kind of elements at play here.
The compute constraints that AI labs are
facing and the implications maybe for
the next
one to five years. This is in a piece
people should check out. It's random
thoughts while gazing at the misty AI
frontier. Good headline by the way.
>> Very dramatic.
>> Yeah, very dramatic. I love it. It's
very evocative. Would you mind explain
Actually, before we move to the compute
constraints cuz I do want you to
talk to that next, but for people who
don't have any real context on the
talent wars and what you were just
mentioning earlier with meta like on the
high end, what do some of these pay
equity packages, compensation
packages look like that are getting
offered?
>> I don't have exact knowledge of the full
range and everything else. The rumors
and the things that have kind of made it
into the press, the claims are that
these things are between tens of
millions and hundreds of millions of
dollars per person.
And again, it's a very small number of
people who get anything that's quite
that outsized.
But I think the basic idea is we're in
one of the most important technology
races of all times.
And the faster that we get to sort of
better and better AI, the more economic
value will effectively show up.
>> Mhm.
>> And therefore, people are really willing
to pay in an outsized way for the
handful of people who are world's best
at this thing.
And 5, 10 years ago, these people were
like well compensated, but it was a
completely different ballgame. They
never just wasn't the core of everything
that's happening in technology, but also
honestly societally and politically, and
you know, for education and health. Like
it's going to have all these really
broad and I think largely positive
implications for the world.
>> Mhm.
>> But it is the moment of transformation,
and so some of these key packages are
going way up.
>> What are the compute constraints that
you discussed in your recent piece?
>> So basically, all the different people
call them labs now. There's OpenAI,
there's Anthropic, there's Google,
there's xAI, etc. All the labs are
basically training these giant models,
and effectively what you do is you buy a
bunch of chips from Nvidia,
and you're actually building out a
system. So you have chips from Nvidia,
you have memory from Hynix and Samsung
and other places, and you're building
out a data center. There's all these
things that go into building these big
systems and data centers and everything
else. And you basically have clusters of
hundreds of thousands or millions or
the scale keeps going up
of systems that you're buying from
Nvidia and from others. Google has their
TPU, there's other systems as well. And
you're using that to basically train an
AI model. And what that means is you're
running huge amounts of data against
these these big clouds, and eventually
the crazy thing is your output or your
model is literally like a flat file.
It's like almost like outputting a text
doc or something. And that text doc is
what you then load to run AI.
Which is insane if you think about it.
You use a giant cloud for months and
months and months and your output is
like a small file.
>> [snorts]
>> And [laughter] that small file is a mix
of representing all of humanity's
knowledge that's available on the
internet plus logic and reasoning and
other things built into it. And you can
kind of think about that in the context
of your brain, right? You have three or
four billion base pairs of DNA, and
that's more than enough to specify
everything about your physical being,
but also your brain and your mind and
how it works and how you can see things
and talk and taste things and all your
senses and everything's just
encapsulated in these very small number
of genes, actually. And so similarly,
you can encapsulate all of human
knowledge into like this flat file,
effectively.
>> How do you think about the constraints,
then? What are the constraints?
>> Every year, the constraint
doling out these big clouds to train AI,
and then also what's known as inference,
where you're actually using these chips
to understand to run the AI system
itself. You need lots and lots of chips
from Nvidia to do this or TPUs or
others, but then you also need other
things. You need packaging to actually
be able to package the chips. And so
there's a whole supply chain around
building out these systems. And
different parts of that supply chain
have constraints on them at different
times. And so right now, the major
constraint is memory, or a specific type
of memory that's largely made by Korean
companies, although there's some broader
providers of it.
And people think that that memory
constraint will exist for about two
years, maybe plus or minus,
because ultimately, the capacity of
those companies has been lower than the
capacity for everything else in the
system. People think other constraints
in the future may literally be building
out the data centers or power and energy
to run these things, right? But for
today, it's this memory.
And so everybody in the industry is
constrained in terms of how much compute
they can buy to throw out these things.
And so what that does is it creates a
ceiling on top of how big you can scale
these models up in the short run.
Cuz every lab is buying as much as it
can, a bunch of startups are buying as
much of these computers as they can.
And everybody's constrained.
What that means though is you have an
artificial ceiling on how big
a model can get in the short run and how
much inference can run or how many
things you can actually do with the AI
right now. And that also means that
you're effectively enforcing a situation
where no one lab can pull so far ahead
of everybody else because they can't buy
10 times as much computers as everybody
else.
And there are these scale laws that the
more compute you have the bigger the AI
model you can build and many cases the
more performing it can be eventually.
And so that may mean that over the next
two years-ish all these labs should be
roughly close to each other because
nobody has the capacity to pull ahead.
And when the constraint comes off there
is some world where you could make an
argument that suddenly somebody can pull
far ahead of everybody else.
So right now OpenAI, Anthropic, Google,
you know, they're they're reasonably
close in terms of capabilities although
some will pull ahead on one thing versus
another.
That should roughly continue everybody
thinks for the next at least two years
because of this.
>> Google is also constrained by
the memory from Samsung, Micron, etc.
They are they are similarly constrained
as the other players.
>> Right now everybody is similarly
constrained.
And you know, a subset of these labs
either are already making their own
chips or systems like Google has TPUs
and other things. Amazon has actually
built its own chips called Traniums. And
so there's basically like different
systems for different companies but
fundamentally all of them are are
limited in terms of how much they can
either manufacture themselves, purchase
themselves.
And a year or two ago the main
constraint was packaging, now it's it's
memory.
Two years from now who knows, maybe
something else. We constantly are
hitting bottlenecks as we're trying to
do this build out.
>> This is probably going to be a naive
question because I'm a muggle and not
able to write technical white papers or
anything approaching that,
but it seems to me that I'm not the
first person to say this, we're better
at forecasting problems than solutions
potentially. And so for instance, way
back in the day the price per gallon of
gasoline or petrol goes above a certain
point, okay, people are forecasting
doom and destruction, but
past a certain price per barrel,
suddenly new means of extraction became
feasible and there were investments made
in things like fracking and so on.
Is there sort of a plausible scenario in
which there is some type of workaround?
>> If you're along those lines, if that
makes any sense. I don't know, maybe
there isn't.
>> As far as I know there so far at least
is not.
>> Mhm.
>> Part of that is because of the way that
some of these things are built and it's
basically
the capacity that you need, for example,
for memory is basically a type of fab.
>> Mhm.
>> And so you need time to build out the
fab and to get the equipment and put the
lines in place.
>> Right.
>> So it's a traditional sort of cap X into
infrastructure cycle.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah, these companies basically under
invested in that. Because they they
didn't quite believe the demand
forecasts that other people had around
this stuff.
>> Mhm.
>> And so now they're trying to catch up.
And so it's it's one of these things
where everybody keeps saying, well, AI
is growing so fast, how can it possibly
keep growing at this rate? But it keeps
growing at this rate. It just keeps
going. And that's because its
capabilities are so impactful and so
important. And so you look at the
revenue of these companies
and it's interesting. I can I can send
you the chart later, but
Jared on my team pulled together a graph
of how long did it take for companies to
get to a billion dollars in revenue and
then from a billion to 10 billion and
then from 10 to like 100. And there's
only a small number of companies that
have ever done that. And you can
literally look by generation of company
how long it took. And so for example, I
can't remember ADP or somebody it took
them 30 years to get to a billion
revenue or whatever it is. And Anthropic
and OpenAI did that in like a year. And
for Google it took four years or
whatever. I don't remember exactly what
the numbers are. But it was kind of like
as you go through these subsequent
generations it gets faster and faster to
get to scale.
Right now OpenAI and Anthropic are each
rumored to be roughly around $30 billion
run rate.
Which is insane.
>> That's crazy.
>> That's 0.1% [snorts]
of US GDP.
So, AI probably went from zero to half a
percent of GDP at least as a as a
revenue contributor.
And you extrapolate out and if they hit
$100 billion in revenue in the next year
or 2 years, whatever it is, then we're
getting close to a place where each of
these companies is a percent or two of
GDP. That's insane if you think about
that.
>> It's bananas. Yeah, it's bananas.
>> That is really actually important and
useful a lot. That doesn't include like
the cloud revenue for Azure for
doing AI stuff or, you know, Google GCP
or Amazon like it's just those two
companies. It's insane.
>> Mhm. I would love to dig into your
thinking cuz you're you're one of the
best
kind of first principles and also
systems thinkers I've met. And
I love having conversations with you
because I always learn something new and
it's not necessarily a data point, but
often it might be a lens
or a framework for thinking about
different things. And that framework
evolves for you as well. But for
instance, if I was looking at this
interview you did, this is a while back
with First Round Capital and you're
talking about sort of market first and
then strength of team second. But you
talked about passing on investing in
Lyft Series C. This was at the time. And
ultimately part of it seemed to hinge on
winner-take-all versus oligopoly versus
other. And I'm curious how you are
thinking about that within the AI space
because I mean, you started skating for
that puck
before almost anyone I know,
if not everyone I know. And this how are
you thinking about that? And this ties
into something that you mentioned in
your piece that I haven't heard
anyone else talking about, but I'll give
the sentence as a cue. I don't think
you'll need it, but founders running
successful AI companies should all take
a cold hard look at exiting in the next
12 to 18 months, which might be a value
maximizing moment for outcomes. And you
sort of went back to
the dot com bust and the sort of
survival rates and then breakout rates.
Could you just explain that sentence
sure and then also explain how you're
thinking about whether you think this
will be winner take all oligopoly like
what type of dynamic you think emerges?
>> In terms of the precedent and that
doesn't mean it's going to happen here,
but if you look at every technology
cycle
90 95 99% of the companies in that cycle
go bust.
>> Mhm.
>> And that dates way back even to what was
high-tech 100 years ago, which was the
automotive industry in Detroit dozens of
car companies and hundreds of suppliers
and it collapsed into a small number of
auto companies eventually. And so this
is not a new story during the internet
cycle or bubble of the 90s
450 companies went public in 99, 450 or
so companies went public in the first
few months of of 2000.
And so that was 900 companies and say
another
500 or 1000 went public in the couple
years before that. So you had somewhere
between 1500 and 2000 companies go
public.
Go public. So that means they kind of
made it.
>> Mhm.
>> And of those how many have survived? A
dozen? Maybe two dozen?
>> Yeah.
>> And so out of 2000 companies 1980
or so went under.
>> Mhm.
>> What form or another. Maybe they got
bought for a little bit.
And so there's no reason to think that
AI cycle will be any different. And
every cycle's like that. SaaS was like
that, automobile was like that and
crypto was like that.
So most companies are not going to make
it. A handful will and we can talk about
those. And so if you're running an AI
company right now, you should ask
yourself what is the nature of the
durability of your company and are you
one of that dozen or two that are going
to be really important 10 years from
now?
Or is now a good moment for you to sell
because what you're doing will start to
get commoditized or will be competed by
a lab, or will be something that the
market will shift or the technology will
shift and you'll become obsolete.
And there's a handful of companies that
will continue to be great. They should
never sell or they should never exit.
They should keep going.
But there's probably a lot of companies
that now or the next 12 to 18 months
is the best moment for them possible in
terms of value that they'll get for what
they're doing. And for every company
there's a value maximizing moment where
they hit their peak. And it's usually a
window. There's usually a you know, 6 to
12 months where what you're doing is
important enough, you're scaling enough,
everything's working before some
headwind hits you.
>> Mhm.
>> And sometimes it's very predictable that
that headwind is coming and you can see
it. And often you see it in the second
derivative of growth. Like how fast are
you growing starts to plateau a little
bit and you're either going to keep
going up or you should sell.
>> Mhm.
>> And so that's really what that's meant
to be. I'm incredibly bullish around AI
as you can tell from the rest of the
conversation.
>> Mhm.
>> And so it's lots about the
transformation that's happening overall
because of this technology.
And more that only a handful are going
to continue to be really important. And
so are you one of them or not? If you're
one of them you should never ever ever
sell.
>> So what are the characteristics of that
handful? The handful that have durable
advantage? Because you look back at 2000
it's like, man, what would you have used
to try to pick out Google and Amazon?
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> And I'm not saying that's the best
comparator, but within the
many avalanche of AI companies
>> Mhm.
>> which of those that you think have
durable advantage? I mean, of course
some of the name brand labs come to
mind. Maybe they become the interface
for everything else, who knows. But how
would you answer that in terms of either
shared characteristics or actual names?
What sets apart the handful that you
think
will make it?
>> I think the core labs will be around for
a while. So that's OpenAI, Anthropic,
Google barring some accident or disaster
or some blow up, but
it seems like they're in a really
durable spot. And to your point on like
market structure, I wrote a Substack
post I don't know 3 years ago or
something predicting that that would
probably be an oligopoly market and
there'd be a handful and they'd be
aligned with the clouds. And that's
roughly kind of what happened. I mean,
there's Meta, there's XAI, and there's
other players that may change this that
didn't exist when I wrote that post.
But it feels to me like in the short run
that's an oligopoly. Like there's no
reason for that to be a monopoly market
unless one of them pulls ahead so much
in capabilities that it just becomes a
default for everyone. And that could
happen. But so far it hasn't. And again,
this compute constraint may prevent that
in the short run or at least provide an
asymptote on it. As you move up the
stack and you see well there's different
application companies, you know, there's
Harvey for legal, there's a Bridge for
health, there's Decagon and Sierra for
customer success. You know, there's
these different companies per
application. There's three or four
lenses that you can look at.
One is if the underlying model gets
better, does your product or service get
dramatically better for your customers
in a way that they still want to keep
using you?
Second, how deep and broad are you going
from a product perspective?
Are you building out multiple products?
Are they all integrated in a cohesive
whole? Is it really being built directly
into the processes in a company in a way
that it's hard to pull out?
Often the issue for companies
in adoption of AI isn't how good is the
AI, it's how much do I have to change
the workflows and the ways that that my
people do things in order to adopt it.
It's about change management usually,
it's not about technology. And so if
you've been able to embed yourself
enough into workflows and how people do
business and how they work and how
everything else kind of ties together,
that tends to be quite durable.
>> Mhm.
>> Are you capturing and storing and using
proprietary data? Sometimes that's
useful. I think data moats in general
are overstated.
But I think sometimes it can be actually
quite useful and that's usually the
system of record view of the world.
So, you know, there's a handful of
criteria around like will this thing be
long-term
defensible or not?
>> Yeah.
>> And the application level that's often
one potential lens on it.
>> Mhm.
>> So, question, if if people are listening
to this and they are in the position of
perhaps a founder who should consider
identifying their
kind of short period of maximum
valuation and perhaps hitting the
parachute in some way, what are the
options? Because I think of some of
these companies, I'm not going to name
them, but there are multiple companies
that have multi-billion dollar
valuations.
>> As you do.
>> There seems to be, again, from a mostly
layperson perspective, I mean
>> [laughter]
>> that the labs
probably can build what they are
currently selling without too much
trouble. Do they aim to be acquired by a
lab, in which case there's sort of a
build versus buy decision for the lab
itself? Are they aiming for one of not
the open AIs or Anthropic's, but maybe
somebody who's trying to get more skin
in the game, like Amazon or fill in the
blank?
What are the exit options?
>> I think there's a lot of exit options,
and the thing that's crazy right now is
if you go back 10 or 15 years
the biggest market cap in the world was
like 300 billion.
>> Mhm.
>> The biggest tech market cap was, I don't
know, 200-ish or something. I think the
biggest one at the time was
Exxon or somebody, like 15 years ago.
>> Mhm.
>> And over the last 10 or 15 years, what
happens is we suddenly ended up with
these multi-trillion dollar market caps,
which everybody thought was nuts at the
time, but things will probably only get
bigger. There will probably be more
aggregation versus less in the biggest
winners.
And there's more and more companies who
have these market caps between say 100
billion and a few trillion.
>> Mhm.
>> In a way, this is unprecedented. And
that means there's enormous buying
power, because 1% of 3 trillion is 30
billion. Right? They can take 1% and pay
30 billion dollars for something, which
is insane, right? That's that's really
unprecedented.
And that means that these really big
acquisitions can happen.
>> For the companies that I'm imagining,
again, I don't want to name names
that may have seem to have a limited
lifespan, right? When I'm in these these
small group threads with friends of mine
who are often time, not always, but I'm
in a bunch of them and when they're
tech investors, very successful tech
investors, and I'm like, "Okay, these
five companies, you've got 10 chips. How
would you allocate your 10 chips?"
There's certain companies that
consistently get zero, even though
they're reasonably well known. Why would
one of the labs buy one of those?
>> Depends on what it is, and it may be a
lab, it may be one of the big tech
incumbents, an Apple, Amazon,
>> Right.
>> Google's kind of both things.
There's Oracle,
>> Mhm.
>> there's Samsung, there's
Tesla, there's SpaceX now in the market
doing things. There's a bunch of
different buyers of different types.
There's Snowflake and Databricks,
there's Stripe,
>> Mhm.
>> Coinbase if you're doing financial
service. There's just a ton of companies
that actually are quite large. That's
kind of the point. And so often you end
up selling to one of four things. You
can sell to one of the big labs or
hyperscalers or giant tech companies.
You can sell to somebody who cares a lot
about your vertical. So for example, a
Thomson Reuters if you're doing legal or
accounting or things that are kind of
related to that.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean, I think actually one thing that
doesn't happen enough is merger of
competitors, particularly private
companies where you can do that. Because
ultimately, if your primary vector is
winning and you're neck and neck with
somebody and you're competing on every
deal and you're destroying pricing for
each other, like maybe it's better to
just merge. It actually was
x.com and PayPal in the '90s, right?
>> Yeah. You and Musk
>> Here you were running different
companies and they merged because they
said we're two people doing this, why
fight?
>> Yeah, or Uber Lyft way back in the day,
right? That might not have been a
merger, it might have been an
acquisition, but it's like
>> Yeah, and the rumor is that that almost
happened and then, you know, that Uber
side walked away from it.
>> Mhm.
>> But all the money that Uber spent on
fighting Lyft for all those years maybe
would have been better spent just buying
them. Maybe not. I don't know the exact
math.
>> Mhm.
>> But often it actually does make sense to
say, "You know what? Like, we'll just
stop fighting it out and we'll just
combine
and just go win. Cuz if the primary
purpose is to win the market, you're
already fighting all these big
incumbents that already exist anyhow.
So, why why make it even harder?
>> As you know, we talk about this a lot,
but we'll talk about
you with your investing hat on. But,
before you even put that, let's call it
full-time investing hat on,
you had a lot in your background that
may or may not have helped you, and I'm
curious if you look at your biology
background, the math background, do you
think any of those things or other
elements materially contributed to how
you think about investing that has given
you an advantage
in
>> [clears throat]
>> I suppose there are different stages to
kind of winning deals, but sometimes
they're not crowded, but let's just talk
about
the selection process.
>> The math stuff helped me, I think, in
two ways. One is
it's helped me
with certain aspects of like
technical or algorithmic CS and
understanding it, and sometimes that's
useful
>> Mhm.
>> in the context of how certain things
work in AI or things like that, or just
fluency of
numbers and data, and
I don't know to call it nerd language or
something.
And I did the math degree, honestly,
just for fun, and I think that's
actually the thing that was helpful.
>> Mhm.
>> We did an undergrad degree in math, so I
didn't go that far with it, but
I did the very sort of abstract pure
math stuff, and I think that was a good
forcing function of how to really think
logically step by step about things, cuz
roughly the way that at least I learned
how to do proofs was you do the logical
sequence, but then sometimes you do
these intuitive leaps and then go back
and try and prove it to yourself.
>> Mhm.
>> Or flesh out the
the reasoning behind that intuitive
leap. And I think sometimes investing is
a little bit like that.
>> When did you first have the inkling
that you could be good at investing?
And that could be investing writ large,
it could be maybe within the context of
our conversations, startups and angel
investing. When did you first kind of
go, "Aha,
yeah, maybe I could be good at this."
Was there a moment or a deal or anything
like that that comes to mind?
>> Not really. I'm really hard on myself,
so even now I second-guess myself a lot.
>> Mhm.
>> Somebody was telling me that the two
people that always beat themselves up
the most in hindsight is me and this one
other person who's another well-known
founder / investor. And so, I don't
think there's a single moment where I'm
like, "Wow, this makes sense for me to
do." I think it just kind of organically
kept going because I was getting into
some very strong companies, and then
you know, that allowed me to sort of
continue what I'm doing, but
>> Okay.
>> Yeah, I wish I had a moment like that.
>> [laughter]
>> God dammit, you need to revise your
genesis story like every every good
founder.
>> Yeah. [laughter]
Yeah, ever since I was seven, I've been
thinking about investing in technology.
[laughter]
>> All right, now we're talking. This is
So, getting into those deals, right?
What allowed you to get into those
deals, right? Because some people have
an informational advantage, and they put
themselves in a position to have an
informational advantage, right? And I
think that had I not I don't want this
to be a leading question, but it's like
had I not moved to Silicon Valley
>> Yeah.
>> when I did, like 2000,
and then subsequently, you know, stayed
there, moved to San Francisco
specifically, like nothing that I was
able to do in angel investing would have
been possible. So, but there's more to
your story cuz a lot of people moved
there with hopes of startup riches in
whatever capacity. Not saying that
that's why you moved there. But
what was it that allowed you to get into
those deals? Maybe there are certain
things that come to mind
based on our prior conversations, but
I'll just leave it at that. Like why
were you able to
get into or select those deals.
>> I think there's what happened early and
what happens now and I think those two
things are different. I think to your
point, the single most important thing
for anybody wanting to break into any
industry is go to the headquarters or
cluster of that industry. Like move to
wherever that thing is.
And all the advice that you can do
anything from anywhere and everything's
remote is all BS. And you see that for
every industry, not just tech. You know,
if you wanted to get into the movie
business, people wouldn't say
"Hey, you can write a film script from
anywhere. You can digitally score from
anywhere. You can edit it from anywhere.
You can film it anywhere." Like go to
Dallas and join their burgeoning
you know, film scene. They'd say, "Go to
Hollywood." And if you want to do
something in finance and you're like,
"Well, you could raise money from
anywhere and come up with trading
strategies and a hedge fund strategy
from anywhere and you could do it from
anywhere."
People wouldn't say, "Hey, go to you
know, whatever, Seattle." They'd be
like, "Go to New York." Or go to XYZ
financial center. So, the same is true
for tech and
Shreyan on my team
has been performing this sort of unicorn
analysis of where is all the private
market cap aggregating for technology.
And traditionally about half of it's
been the US and then half of that has
been the Bay Area. But with AI, 91% of
private technology market cap is the Bay
Area. 91% of the entire global set of AI
market cap is all in one 10 by 10 area,
right?
So, if you want to do stuff in AI, you
should probably be in the Bay Area.
>> Mhm.
>> Probably the secondary place is New York
and then after that it drops off a
cliff. And really it's the Bay Area.
If you want to do defense tech, you
probably should be in
Southern California, close to where
SpaceX and Anduril are in sort of
Irvine, Orange County, etc. Or El
Segundo, there's a lot of startups
there.
If you want to do fintech and crypto,
maybe it's New York. But the reality is
these are very strong clusters. So, to
your point, number one is I was just in
the right location.
I was in the right networks and I
default was I was running a startup
myself. I was at Google for many years
and then I left to start a company
and people just start coming to me for
advice and the way I ended up investing
in Airbnb is as helping them when they
were eight people or something raise
their series A
and I introduced them to a bunch of
people and helped with some of the
strategy there in very light ways,
right? They would have done it without
me, but and they said, "Hey, at the end
of it, do you want to invest a little
bit?" I said, "Great. That sounds
wonderful." So, it's very organic. Or
the way I invested in Stripe is
I'd sold sort of infrastructure early
API company to Twitter and when Twitter
was say 90 people or so and I sent an
email to Patrick, the CEO of Stripe,
just saying, "Hey, I've heard great
things about you and I really like what
Stripe is doing and I would use it for
my own startup and I I sold this API
company myself. Do you want to just talk
about this stuff?"
And so, we went on a couple walks and
then
a week or two later he texts me and he's
like, "Hey, we're doing a round. Do you
want to invest?"
So, the first few things that I did were
very organic where the founders were
like, "We want you on board."
>> Mhm.
>> I didn't think, "Oh, I should be an
investor and I'm going to chase things.
I'm going to I just really like talking
to smart people and I like to working on
certain business problems and I love
technology and its translation to the
world. And so, it's very like
you know, I was just a nerd and I I met
other nerds and we hit it off. That's
kind of the early like story for me.
>> It just struck me that
I'm sure people have heard or I'm sure
you've heard this before, but you know,
if you want money, ask for advice and if
you want advice, ask for money. It just
struck me that it kind of goes the other
way around, too. It's like
if you offer a bunch of advice, often
times you get to give money and if you
try to give money
>> Yeah.
>> you might get solicited for advice.
>> Yeah, yeah, that's a good point.
>> When did you write The High Growth
Handbook? When [clears throat] was that
published?
>> It's a while ago now. It's probably like
seven-ish years ago, something like
that.
>> Seven years ago. All right. We're going
to come back to that in a minute.
Because you you were in the right place
geographically speaking, right? You were
in the center of the switchboard.
And like you said, these some of these
initial kind of standout investments
came about very organically.
And
what I be curious to hear because you
also said yourself not too long ago that
there's there's what I did then, there's
what I did now. There's also what you
did in between, right along the way.
And I'm wondering for instance if you
would still stand by this. This is from
that first round interview I was
mentioning. As a general rule when I
make investments, it's market first and
the strength of the team second. And
there's more to it. But would you still
agree with that?
>> 90% yes. Everyone's going to meet
somebody exceptional and you just back
them.
Or something may be so early. Like when
I led the first round of Perplexity.
>> Mhm.
>> Like the very very first round.
And the way that came about was Arvin,
the CEO, just I think he like pinged me
on LinkedIn. Literally. And this is why
nobody was doing anything in AI and he
was like an OpenAI engineer or
researcher and he's like, "Hey, I'm at
OpenAI." which nobody cares about at the
time.
And I'm thinking of doing something in
AI and I heard that you're talking about
this stuff and nobody else is talking
about it and can we meet up?
And so we just started meeting every 2
weeks and brainstorming, right? And then
that led to like investing in that. And
that was kind of a people first thing
where he was just so good. And every
time we talk, he'd show up a week later
with a thing that we discussed built.
Like who does that?
>> Yeah, that's a good sign.
>> So good.
>> Mhm.
>> Or [clears throat] the way I ended up
investing in Anduril was Google shuts
down Maven, which was their sort of
defense project.
And so I think, well, if if the
incumbents aren't going to do it, what a
great place for startups to play.
Cuz there's been a long history of
Silicon Valley in the defense industry.
That's HP and that's a lot of the, you
know, early brands.
And so I was just looking for something,
or somebody to work on this area and it
was very unpopular at the time.
And I ran into I think it was Trae
Stephens, who's one of the co-founders
of Anduril, who's also at Founders Fund.
It's launch or something else again,
right city to be in. And he said, "Oh,
I'm working on this new defense thing."
And I said, "Amazing. Let's talk about
it." Sometimes it's just looking for
these things too in a market and
sometimes it's people. So Anduril was
looking for a market and then finding
amazing people. Perplexity was kind of
in between where it was like I was
looking at everything in AI
cuz I thought it was going to be
incredibly important, but not very many
people were. And then I just ran across
an exceptional individual.
And that's when I funded OpenAI, that's
when I funded Harvey, which is the early
legal tech. I funded a lot of really
early stuff cuz they were the only
people doing anything in this market
that I thought would be really
important.
>> Let me come back to a few things you
said. So, you mentioned the Perplexity
founder or later the founder who said
you're you're talking about this stuff,
right? Or he heard or read or found you
talking about this stuff.
>> Yeah.
>> Where was that? Was that post on your
blog? Was it somewhere else? How did he
actually find you talking about
anything?
>> I mean, I think he pinged me in part
because I was involved with a bunch of
the prior wave of technology companies,
Airbnb, Stripe, Coinbase,
Instacart, Square, a bunch of stuff like
that. And so, I think at that point I
was already known as
founder and investor.
But then in top of that, I was just I
was trolling AI researchers and just
asking them about what's going on
because it was so interesting. There was
a bunch of art that was being done with
these things called GANs at the time,
these generative adversarial networks.
And so, I was playing around with that.
I tried to hire engineers to build me
effectively what was Midjourney cuz I
just thought it'd be really cool to be
make it easy to make AI art.
>> Okay, so let let me pause for a second
because this is my second question and
it's a good time.
When you mentioned, you know, AI, I
thought it would be incredibly
important.
>> Yeah.
>> What were the
indicators of that, right? What was the
smoke in the distance where you're like,
"Oh, that's an interesting direction."
>> I think there was two or three things.
AI was one of those things that people
have always talked about. So, when I was
doing my math degree, I took a lot of
kind of theoretical CS classes and there
were the early neural network classes
and things like that. And the math
behind it. And and so, there's always
this promise of building these
artificial intelligences of different
forms.
And one could argue Google was a AI
company. And back then it was called
machine learning and it was different
technology bases in some sense and I
think 2012 was when AlexNet came out and
there was this proof that you can start
scaling things and have really
interesting characteristics in terms of
how AI systems work and then 2017 is
when the team at Google invented the
transformer architecture which
everything is based on now or roughly
everything. And so for example, if you
look at GT for chat GPT, the T stands
for transformer. And around 2020-ish, I
think was when GPT-3 came out. And that
was such a big step from GPT-2 and it
still wasn't good enough to really do
stuff with.
But you you're like, oh [__] the
scaling law papers are out.
The step function and capabilities was
huge. You suddenly have a generalizable
model available via an API that anybody
can ping.
And so just extrapolate that out to the
next step and this is going to be really
important.
>> Mhm.
>> So it's basically looking at that
capability step and playing around with
the technology and then reading the
scaling law papers. Or just in general,
the the scaling laws seem to work for
everything. And you're like, wow, this
is going to be really really important.
So let me start getting involved with
it.
>> Do you think you would have or could
have done that without a mathematics
background? I'm I'm guessing there were
probably some other folks, but that
leads me to the question of like, how
are you finding and ingesting that,
right? Was it the talk of the town? So
it was in a sense like within your
social circles and the networks that
you're a part of?
It was a open discussion so you were
engaged with it or are you ingesting
vast quantities of information from
different fields and this happened to be
something that really caught your
attention?
>> I guess it's three things. I mean, I've
always ingested a lot of information
from a lot of different fields just cuz
I like learning about stuff. And I was
always this mix of like math and biology
and anime and art and other things. So,
you know, it was always kind of a mix.
And then it was something that my
friends were talking about, but it was a
bit more like toy-like. Oh, this is cool
and look at what came out. But most
people didn't then extrapolate. It's
kind of like early crypto or Bitcoin.
Like everyone was talking about it, but
very few people bought it. Mhm. And so I
think that was part of it. And then
third, honestly, I just thought it was
really neat stuff that I kept playing
around with. This is back to the GAN
stuff and the art where
these different models would come out
and you could mess around with them. And
one of the things that's really under
discussed in terms of the
importance of it relative to this wave
of foundation models in AI and
everything else is the way AI or machine
learning used to work
is
your team at a company or wherever else
would go and there'd be what's known as
an ML ops team, operations team whose
whole thing was like helping you set up
all the data and the pipelines and
everything to train a model. And you
train a model that was custom to your
use case and what you were trying to
accomplish.
And then it was
you had to build a bunch of internal
services to interact with that model. So
it's a huge pain
to get to the point where you had a
working ML system up and running in
production.
And then suddenly you have a thing where
you're just doing an API call.
So with a line of code or a few lines of
code, anybody anywhere in the world can
ping it. But not just that, it's
generalizable. So it's not just
specialized to one use case like
spell correction or whatever, you can
use it for anything. And it has all
the internet embedded in it in some
sense in terms of a knowledge base.
>> Mhm.
>> And it can start having these advanced
reasoning capabilities. But one of the
most important things is hey, you can
get it with a couple lines of code. You
don't have to go and build an ML ops
team. You have to host it. You have to
interact with it. You don't have to do
all this extra stuff. It just works.
>> Mhm.
>> That's really important.
>> It's huge.
>> Yeah.
>> [laughter]
>> It's hard kind of hard to overstate. I
have a million questions for you. The
problem with this is like the
embarrassment of riches of directions
that we could go.
>> Mhm.
>> So I am using and my team Claude code
and assorted tools for all sorts of
stuff right now, right? And
one of them, it just so happens,
overlaps with an area of
great skill for you and experience,
>> [laughter]
>> which is
angel investing. So this is the first
time where I feel really enabled to do
and there is some manual effort involved
as you might imagine, but to go back and
do an analysis of 20 years of angel
investing.
>> Mhm.
>> To try to do any number of things. And I
suspect that a lot of what interests me
is not particularly useful. Like doing
some counterfactuals, what if I had held
each of these for 3 years, for 5 years,
for whatever. I mean, that's kind of
like just opus day whipping myself in
the back
>> Yeah.
>> for the most part. But, in doing an
analysis like that, there's certain
things that immediately come to mind for
me that might be of interest and I want
to hear what you would do if you would
even do this. I mean, part part of it is
frankly just curiosity, right? Are the
stories I tell myself about this
true
or not?
>> Yeah.
>> And so, I'm interested like who made
certain introductions. Are there certain
people who just took me there, basically
people on in hospice care and like
shipped them over as like a last-ditch
effort? Are there people who actually
sent me good stuff consistently, etc.,
etc.
>> Mhm.
>> So, there are a million and one ways I
could try to interrogate the data and
enrich it. We're doing a pretty good job
of enriching it. I mean, Claude is and
other tools, you know, open ads very
good at this.
What are some of the more interesting
questions or lines of kind of
examination, you think, looking back
like whatever it is?
In my case, it's about roughly 20 years
of stuff.
>> The weird thing I've been doing is
uploading pictures of founders and
asking the models to predict if they'd
be good founders.
>> Oh, wow. Okay.
>> Because if you think about it, we do
this all the time when we meet people,
right? We quickly try to create an
assessment of that person and their
personality and what they're like and
there's all these micro features. Like,
do you have crow's feet by your eyes
which suggests that your smiles are
genuine and what does that imply about
the sense of humor you have or furred
your brow over time and what does that
mean? You know, so there's all these
like micro features.
And when you meet people, you actually
can get a pretty quick impression of
them pretty fast. It doesn't mean it's
correct, right?
>> Mhm.
>> But we actually do this really fast as
people.
>> Mhm.
>> So I have this whole like set of prompts
that I've been messing around with just
for fun
around can you extrapolate like what a
person's personality based off of a few
images?
>> Uh.
>> And therefore can you be predictive
about their behavior in any way? I think
that's fun, right?
>> Yeah. Are you finding [clears throat]
any signal there?
>> Yeah, it works pretty well.
>> Wow.
>> So I've been doing the weird [__]
right?
>> Practice smiling, people.
>> Yeah, yeah. I think it's interesting,
right? Because
we do this all the time where we read
people, right? And that's part of the
prompt. It's like you're a very good
cold reader of people based on micro
features and etc. etc. Kind of spell it
out and then based on that not only give
me your interpretation of this person,
but explain the specific micro features
for each thing that you're stating about
the person.
>> Mhm.
>> And they're going to break it down for
you.
>> Mhm.
>> It's amazing. Like imagine what this
technology is. It's crazy. And again,
I'm not saying it's fully accurate and
I'm not saying it'll be predictive and
all that, but
it's done pretty well in terms of
nailing people. It's even done things
like, "Oh, this person probably has this
type of sense of humor." Or this person
probably holds themselves back in most
social settings and then chimes in with
a witty wry thing that nobody expects or
whatever. I mean, it's very specific.
>> Very specific.
>> Wow. [laughter]
It's amazing, right? And so I've been
doing stuff like that,
which may not be that your question, but
I've been finding it really fun.
>> It's related, right? In the sense that
and I'm sure I'm missing some steps, but
I I love angel investing and I the dose
makes the poison. So there's usually a
case to be made
when I get to a certain threshold, I'm
like, "Okay, this isn't fun anymore."
Like I love dark chocolate, too, but I
don't want just to be force-fed dark
chocolate all day. But and you know,
I've talked about this, right? But I
really do enjoy the learning and the
sport of it, frankly, and interacting
with some very, very smart people. Not
not all of them work out as far as the
founders of companies, but
ultimately, I'm going to try to figure
out how to separate signal from noise.
And also, it's fun to try to use
anything, but in this case, investing,
to sharpen your own thinking, right? And
to stress test your own beliefs and the
assumptions that undergird some of your
predictions, things like that. I'm just
wondering if you've ever done like sort
of a retrospective analysis of your
startup investing or if you're like,
"No, more Mark Andreessen style, only
forward." [snorts]
>> Yeah. Early on, when I was first
starting to invest, I would have this
long grid of things by which I would
score each company.
And then I'd go back and see if it was
correct. It was roughly correct. I think
the hard part is there's a lot of like
randomness in outcomes.
There's the company that sells for a few
billion dollars that you thought was
dead, or whatever it is.
>> Sure.
>> Andreessen style. How do you score
things like that? Right now, we're in
this really weird market moment where
trillions of dollars of market cap are
all chasing the same prize. And so,
they're going to do all sorts of stuff
that wouldn't happen normally.
>> Mhm.
>> So, it's really hard to account for that
kind of thing, right? Relative to all
this, I'm much more in the Mark
Andreessen camp of like, I think very
little about the past. I think
close to zero about my own past. I just
I'm like, let's keep going.
And maybe that's bad, and there should
be dramatically more self-reflection. I
try to self-reflect in the moment, but I
don't try to re-extrapolate and examine
my entire life and decisions and
>> Mhm.
>> If anything, most of the decisions have
been ones where I'm really upset with
myself for not being more aggressive on
something. In other words, I invested in
the company, but I should have tried
even harder to invest more, even if I
tried really, really hard, because
there's a handful of companies that
really matter,
and that's all that kind of matters as
an investor. Obviously, as a person, I
enjoy getting involved with different
companies and different founders and
helping them, whether I think it works
or not, or I think the technology is
interesting, or whatever.
But the reality is, from a returns
perspective
there's a very clear power law that
people talk about and it's true. And I
remember a friend of mine did this
analysis. I think it may have been
Yuri Milner or someone where it's like
look at all the companies from like
I don't remember the exact dates, 2000
or 2004 until today
in technology.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> And it was something like 100 companies
drove like 90-something percent of all
the returns.
>> Mhm.
>> And 10 companies total
drove
like 80% of all returns over a
two-decade period
in technology.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> If you weren't in that 10 companies
you were a bad investor.
>> Mhm.
>> And once you start dealing with these
power laws and these outsize outcomes,
how can you rate that, right? It's
basically did you hit one of 10 things
or not? That's really the rating. That's
probably the correct rating for
investment.
>> I'd love to try to focus on some
early-ish decisions
on this podcast, right? Because like you
said, there are the early decisions,
there's how you did things then, there's
how you're doing things now, which isn't
to say that one is better than the
other, but certainly what you do in the
past tends to inform what you're able to
do and what you do in the present. And
what I'm curious about
and we won't spend a ton of time on
this, but it might be interesting to
folks is to discuss
when you moved from purely doing angel
investing yourself
to
involving other investors in your deals,
right? And
there are multiple ways to do this, but
the reason I want to ask this is because
you did a number of
>> [snorts]
>> SPVs. I'll explain what that is, special
purpose vehicle, but for folks, you
might be familiar with venture capital
firm, they have funds and they raise,
let's just call it $100 million for a
fund.
That can be more or less, of course.
Then they invest in a bunch of different
[clears throat] companies and then you
sort of see
who wins, who lose, and then if there
are profits, I guess conventionally,
let's just use the textbook example, the
venture capital firm takes 20% of the
upside and then the the LPs, the
investors get 80% and the venture
capital firm takes a management fee to
keep the lights on, although it usually
does a lot more than keep the lights on.
With the SPVs, you're investing in,
let's just say for simplicity, a single
company, right?
And there are advantages to that in
simplicity for somebody who's putting
together the SPV, but you also have a
lot of reputational risk. Because if you
have a fund, and you have a couple of
losers, your investors don't
automatically go to zero, right? But if
you have an SPV and it goes to zero,
>> [snorts]
>> that could really hurt you
reputationally. And when I look at some
of your early SPVs, which I think
included certainly a number of name
brands, like Instacart and so on, how
did you choose
which companies to do the SPVs with,
right? Because that seems like a very
important set of decisions to lay the
groundwork for creating optionality for
what you do after that.
>> I think to your point, I've always been
terrified of losing other people's
money. Like I'm fine if I lose my own
money.
>> Mhm.
>> It's my decision, I'm an adult, it's
okay, but I've always been people give
me money or adults or institutions, etc.
Invest on their behalf, but somehow
we're there, I was just terrified of
ever losing money for people. And so
I've tried over time to be judicious
behind the SPVs that I did early on and
the focus was on things that I thought
would really be
out sized companies. And so that was to
your point, Instacart, it was early
Stripe, it was Coinbase, there was a
couple things like that that were
amongst my very first SPVs. And the
emphasis was very much on, do I think
this can be a massive thing? And also,
do I think there's enough downside
protection in some sense that even if it
didn't work as well as I thought, it
would still be a good outcome for
people. So yeah, I try to do that very
diligently.
It's interesting because a lot of people
ping me for help as they think about
becoming investors or their scouts for a
fund, which means basically they're
given a small amount of money by a
venture capital fund. Sequoia famously
has this program they give people money
and then those people invest money
on their behalf and some of the scouts
that I've talked to
basically treat it like free money or an
option. They're just kind of like, "Oh,
let's throw it at a bunch of stuff.
Maybe something works."
And I pointed out to them, "Hey, if if
you actually want to become a
professional investor at some point,
this is kind of your track record."
>> Mhm.
>> A, you're a fiduciary in some sense and
maybe you have to work on that
perspective, but B,
you know, this will establish like your
track record and do you want to have a
good one or a bad one and how do you
think about that? And again, sometimes
people just get lucky and they hit the
one thing out of a hundred, but that
more than returns everything and they
look great.
But it's hard to be consistently good at
this stuff or consistently hit great
companies.
>> I want to double click on a few things
you said and maybe you could walk us
through a pseudonymous example. Doesn't
need to be a named company, but when
you're talking about setting your track
record, right? You did an excellent job
of that before you then went on later to
raise funds and so on.
And I would love you to perhaps explain
some of the things you do in diligence
or how you weight things differently and
also how you think about like the capped
minimum downside. I'm not sure that's
the exact wording that you used
in selecting those deals, right? Because
you could have selected any number of
deals. On a sort of due diligence level,
what's the kind of stuff that you focus
on maybe more than others and what are
the things you pay less attention to
than others?
>> I think there's a big difference between
early and late things.
>> Mhm.
>> On the early side, to the point earlier,
I tend to spend a lot more time in the
market than most early stage investors.
Most early stage investors say, "I just
care about the team and human and how
good are they?"
>> Mhm.
>> But I've seen amazing teams crushed by
terrible markets and I've seen
reasonably crappy teams do very well and
so,
you know, at this point I think the
market is more important, although I
think obviously great teams can find
their way if they decide to shift around
a bit.
>> Mhm.
>> I index a lot on market early and that
may be customer calls or maybe it's
trying to understand do I think
something could be big? It could just be
some intuition around hey, you know,
defense is really important. Nobody's
doing defense. Let me find a defense
company, right? I tend to index a lot on
that. And relatedly, I've tended to
avoid science projects. And there's some
people who get really distracted by wow,
this is really cool. It's quantum and
it's this and it's that. And I've
largely avoided those things. And you
know, sometimes I miss things that were
really good, but often
that was the right call. I actually
think SPACs saved sort of hard tech and
science-based investing industry because
if you look at what happened basically
at the market peak, a bunch of SPACs
took a bunch of companies public that
would not have been able to raise money
in private markets later.
And they gave enough money to keep
going, but more importantly, they
returned a bunch of money to these hard
tech funds. And that saved them from
going under. It gave them all the
returns with basically the SPAC era. So,
Chamath basically saved hard tech. I
mean I mean that seriously, not
tongue-in-cheek.
>> Huh.
>> And I largely avoided that kind of class
of companies. And I'm not saying it was
smart. I would have made money off of
it. I just thought their results were
sort of capitalization issues and
science risk and market risk and other
things to them. For later stage stuff,
>> [snorts]
>> the hard part often is everything on
paper gets modeled out for a late-stage
company as a two to three X from that
investment point.
>> [laughter]
>> Right.
>> Because all the funds that are driving
the rounds underwrite against some IRR
clock, 25% IRR, whatever it is.
And so, they all come up with these
models. And then the models all say all
these companies are basically going to
two to three X. And the art there
or the science there, whatever you want
to call it, is is that a 0.5 X company?
Is it going to drop in value or is that
a 10 X? And how do you know it's a 10 X
versus a two to three X versus a 0.5?
And that's the harder part of growth
investing. And there's a subset of
things that you're like, this thing will
just keep going. And here's why. But
often it's not mathematical. Often
that's just like some market dynamic or
some core insight or some market share
question. And people tend to make that
stuff really complicated. And they have
these really complicated multi-page
models and 50-page memos and all the
rest.
And often these things boil down to one
single question.
What is the one thing I need to believe
about this company that makes me think
it's going to continue to be really big?
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> If it's three things, it's too
complicated. It's probably not going to
work. If it's no things, then it doesn't
make much sense. So, usually there's one
or two things that are really the core
insights you need to understand like
the outcome for something.
>> Could you give an example of one of
those beliefs for any company that comes
to mind?
>> I'll give you two or three of them. I
mean,
Coinbase, part of it was just hey, this
is an index on crypto and crypto will
keep growing. Cuz if Coinbase trades
every main cryptocurrency and they take
a cut of every transaction and have
enough volume to effectively bought a
basket of every cryptocurrency by
investing in Coinbase.
>> Mhm.
>> That was the premise there. Stripe, it
was they're an index on e-commerce and
e-commerce will keep growing back then.
Now, it's much more complex and there's
all sorts of great drivers of its
performance. Anduril was hey, machine
vision and drones are going to be
important. AI and drones are going to be
important for defense.
>> That's it.
>> I mean, it was more complicated than
that. I'm just saying like that was the
fundamental
>> Well, that was it for the belief, for
the core belief.
>> It was like cost plus model versus
hardware margin. You know, Anduril
actually had four or five things that
were important there
that were kind of like a checklist for a
defense tech company, but for a lot of
the other ones, it was like
e-commerce is good.
>> This is probably too inside baseball,
but what were the stages of the
companies that you mentioned when you
created the SPVs, roughly?
>> Well, I first invested in Stripe when it
was like eight people and then I kept
following on and I ran out of my own
money, frankly, and that's when I
started doing SPVs.
So, I think I did my first SPV in Stripe
around the series C, ish.
>> Mhm.
>> Right in there.
>> Something like that.
>> Got it. And were the others more or less
similar, ish? Instacart, etc.
>> Yeah, they're probably roughly in that
ballpark, C, D, kind of that that range.
>> Mhm.
>> I didn't have funds and everything else
and you know, I was putting as much as I
could personally into these things.
Both the earlier, but honestly, I just
kept going when I could.
>> When you're looking at trying to
determine if something is a 0.5x or a
10x, in addition to the core belief,
what are other layers of due diligence
that you bring to bear on trying to
ascertain that, where something falls on
that spectrum?
>> Oh, I mean, I do enormous due diligence.
So, meet with the CFO multiple times,
walk through all the financials, walk
through the financial model, walk
through customers, call customers, look
at executive team, you know, it's it's a
bunch of stuff.
>> Mhm.
>> My fund is the only one I know that
actually does like cash reconciliations,
where we'll go through and do a cash
audit
to look at cash flows for later-stage
things.
So, I do enormous diligence cuz I want
to make sure I'm not doing something
inappropriate, but the flip side of it
is most of it just collapses into like
what's the one thing.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> So, when I work with a company, I
actually try to be very
fast and straightforward on the
diligence in terms of saying, "Let's
just talk about A, we need to just make
sure financials are correct." And if
you, you know, like there's the basics,
but like
let's collapse it down into one or two
core questions, right? That help us
understand if this thing will keep
going, not here's the 30 pages of
questions that don't matter.
>> [laughter]
>> Right.
>> Yeah, right.
>> Which is what a lot of people, they're
like, "Hey, we need to know the
secondary cohort on this [__] thing
that's like a tiny product that who
cares?"
>> [laughter]
>> They just waste time. They waste the
founder's time and the team's time, and
I try very, very hard not to do that as
a former
entrepreneur myself, I know how precious
the time is, and I know how annoying
those questions are.
>> I was actually going to, at one point,
ask you about this, but we don't need to
spend too much time on it. You have a
post, this is from from a while back,
2011, listing questions a VC will ask a
startup. You omitted some of the
questions like the one that you just
mentioned, but I am curious if any of
these questions or additional questions
come to mind when you are talking to
founders. Could be early-stage or
later-stage that you actually apply
yourself. And I know it's from 2011, so
I'm not expecting you to remember the
the post itself.
>> I haven't looked at that post in a
really long time. I'm actually writing
another book now that is sort of the
zero to one startup phase, and it gets
into some questions like that.
>> Mhm.
>> I think the reality is venture capital
has changed dramatically since I wrote
that post, right? Because in 2011
the venture capital funds were largely
doing seeds through series D E maybe and
then companies would go public.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah, this whole 20-year private company
thing didn't exist.
>> Do you know why there's a four-year vest
on stock?
>> No, why is that? I can kind of guess now
that we're talking about IPOs, but go
ahead. Why?
>> In the 1970s they came up with a
four-year vest on stock options for
employees because companies would go
public within four years and so then
you're done.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah, [laughter] yeah.
>> Literally, right?
And so it was like a four-year clock
usually.
>> Yeah.
>> And then when Google took six years to
go public everybody's like, "Oh my gosh,
it took them so long to go public. It
>> [laughter]
>> took years." Like they just sat on their
hands. Do you know what I mean?
>> Yeah.
>> Literally people would say that, right?
>> Mhm.
>> And so what happened is venture capital
used to be very early stage and then
what we now call growth investing was
public market investing, right? That was
a stop that people in the public markets
would do after four or five years of a
company's life. And so the public
markets used to be involved very early.
>> Mhm.
>> And then as Sarbanes-Oxley came out and
companies decided they didn't want to go
public and there was more private
capital available, the timeline until
going public stretched out, right? And
so suddenly venture capital firms are
doing all the growth investing that used
to be public market investing.
>> Mhm.
>> And in 2011 that really wasn't happening
much. It was kind of Yuri Milner from
DST and a few other folks, but it wasn't
that much of an industry.
And so the nature of venture capital has
shifted radically over the last 15
years. And that means that those
questions
that I listed there didn't include what
I'd consider more growth-centric
questions because there wasn't a lot of
growth investing in venture.
>> What would be the examples of
growth-centric questions?
>> Honestly, it would overlap with some of
the earlier stages, you know, by the
time you hit a very late stage it's very
financially driven.
>> Mhm.
>> And so often what at least I and my team
look at is what is just the core
business and how do we extrapolate that
going
and then what are these ancillary things
that the company's doing that are almost
like options in the future that may or
may not come through. And so usually we
base our
investment on that core. Can they just
keep doing the thing they're doing
forever? Cuz most companies mainly get
big off of one thing, at least for the
first decade, right? Yeah. There's a
very few companies that end up with
multiple things that all work. Usually
it's one thing and then 10 years later
you maybe come up with a second thing
that really works, right?
>> Mhm.
>> It's like Google Cloud for Google.
Though obviously there's YouTube and
there's a whole bunch of other stuff.
And Waymo and all these interesting
things now. But it took a while, right?
For a long time it was just search.
Search and ads.
>> Mhm.
>> But then sometimes there are these extra
things that are potentially really
interesting drivers on a business. Like
SpaceX was launch and then it became
satellite, right? Became Starlink.
>> Yeah, man.
Starlink.
What a thing.
It's too bad I have so much tree cover
here.
Can't use it anywhere I spend time. But
let's turn to the high growth handbook
for a second. So that that was let's
just call it seven-ish years ago. It is
an outstanding book. People should
really check it out, especially if
you're playing in the venture-backed
game. What's the subtitle? The subtitle
is scaling startups from 10 to 10,000
people.
>> [snorts]
>> There's a lot of good advice in this
book. I wanted to ask you if there's
anything in this book that you wish
startup founders, the book was intended
for, would pay more attention to or if
there's anything that you would add or
expand
to the book.
>> So when I wrote the book, I had an
outline for it that was two, three times
the length of the actual book in terms
of chapters.
There was a lot of stuff I didn't write
about sales and marketing and growth and
a bunch of other other stuff.
But the book was basically written as
sort of like a tactical guide. It wasn't
meant to be read uh from start to
finish. There's a bunch of interviews
with different people who were I think
amongst the best practitioners in the
world in those areas. But fundamentally
it was meant to be more like you're
suddenly involved with the M&A, jump to
the chapter and read that and then put
it aside until you something else comes
up around hiring that you need to look
at or whatever. And so it really is
meant to be like a
handbook or guide or companion to a
founder versus hey, I'm just going to
read it start to finish and
there'll be some pithy quotes in it or
whatever or one concept over 500 pages.
You know, I try to avoid stuff like
that.
>> [laughter]
>> It's very practical. It's very
changeable. It's very specific.
And this new book that I'm working on is
basically the zero to one version of
that.
>> Mhm.
>> It's like how do you hire your first
five employees as a startup? How do you
somebody tries to buy you, what do you
do?
How do you raise your first round of
funding? You know, it's that kind of
stuff. So that's it's kind of like the
zero to one tactical guide.
>> Let me ask you about one specific
section. I think this is chapter two.
This is on boards.
And if this is getting too in the weeds,
tell me we can hop to something else,
but I am curious if you could talk about
there are two things. Take a better
board member over slightly higher
valuation and if you want to revise
these, that's fine, too. But there are
two things I'd love to hear you talk
about just because this is something
that
you know, founders I've been involved
with bump up against constantly.
Take a better board member over slightly
higher valuation and then write a board
member job spec. And then it
specifically for independents maybe we
I'd love to hear you
maybe just elaborate, but could you
speak to either both of those a bit? And
if you want to take a different
direction, I mean, it's really just
boards writ large.
>> So I think when founders pull together
boards, often the early boards are
investors because investors ask for a
board seat as part of it or as part of
the investment.
And sometimes the founders want somebody
on board who's really committed to the
company and will help out extra and to
some extent when somebody takes a board
seat, it really means or it should mean
that they're all in to help you versus
you can have lots and lots of investors
be a very few board members. Reid
Hoffman has this thing which is like a
board member
at its best is like a co-founder that
you wouldn't be able to hire otherwise
and so you bring them onto your board.
It's somebody that you want to spend
more time with on specific issues
related to the company.
>> Mhm.
>> Fundamentally, your board should be able
to help with different areas of the
company. It could be strategic
direction. It could be closing term
sheets. It could be product areas. It
could be customer intros. it could be a
variety of things. And usually you want
to kind of think of your board members
as a portfolio of people. It's going to
change between an early stage company
and a
late stage and a public one. You have
only different types of people every
time usually.
But most companies are very reactive on
their board versus proactive.
>> Mhm.
>> And so they tend to end up with a couple
investors and then they kind of add
somebody from an industry
seat and they don't really think through
like who they want and why. And
if your co-founder is kind of like your
spouse, your work spouse, your work
husband or your work wife,
your board members are like your
in-laws.
You know, you have to see them on
Thanksgiving and you have to chat with
them all the time. And so hopefully you
have somebody you want to see all the
time and who's helpful and wonderful and
the bad version is like ugh, it's the
like father-in-law or mother-in-law
who's always like berating you or
whatever. And so
you kind of need to find the right
person and it's for many, many years,
right? You end up sometimes with people
on your board for a decade and if
they're an investor you can't get rid of
them.
>> You literally can't fire this person.
>> Mhm.
>> Cuz they have a contractual ability to
be on your board because of the
investment.
So that's why it's really important to
figure out the right person and that's
back to valuation. Sometimes founders
will take a better price from a worse
person because of a better price.
And our mutual friend Naval has this
great quote that valuation is temporary
but control is forever.
>> [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Very Naval.
>> And I think that's very true and so if
you're choosing a board member and part
of that is a control thing, people who
control the board can in some cases fire
the CEO. You really want to choose the
right people and maybe take a worse
price for somebody who's really going to
be helpful and they're minimally
non-destructive and
hopefully good to have around for 10
years.
>> Any other books or resources for people
outside of
the High Growth Handbook who
specifically want to learn about boards,
recruiting, incentivizing
the co-founders that you couldn't hire
to join the board, etc., etc.
Any particular approach you would take
there if they wanted to get more
conversant?
>> I don't have anything super useful
there. I think the best thing is to call
other founders, other people who have
had a people on their board and
see how they approached it. I do think
writing up a job spec, you write a job
spec for everything else in your
company, why wouldn't you write one for
a board member?
>> Mhm.
>> So, it's in to write that up and say
what am I actually looking for and why
and what am I optimizing for so there's
a common view of that.
You can use search firms, you can ask
people, you can target people that you
know,
you know, if you have angel investors,
getting to know them is a great way to
see if you want to add one of them
eventually to your board.
>> Mhm.
>> That's what we did at Color. We
eventually added Sue Wagner, who was a
co-founder of BlackRock,
>> Oh.
>> onto our board. Her other board seats
were Apple,
BlackRock, and Swiss Re. When she joined
our board, I just got to know her
through just like she invested and we
just started working together and really
enjoyed her feedback and insights and so
we added her to the board there. So,
it's kind of like that. You you kind of
want to maybe get to know some
>> Mhm.
Next I want to come to our We were
joking earlier about the in some case
sort of revisionist history
genesis stories.
>> Yeah.
>> So, I'm looking at this is from 2018.
This is a while back. This is
on Y Combinator's blog and you're being
interviewed about the high growth
handbook, but this sort of end of this
piece that I'm looking at says, "These
stories are never told. People will
always say, 'Oh, these things just grew
organically and isn't it amazing?'"
But almost every company that ended up
tens of billions or hundreds of billions
in market cap did this, which is like
taking an aggressive approach to
distribution.
>> Mhm.
>> Whether that's Google and the Firefox
story or Facebook running ads against
people's names in Europe. I just wanted
to hear you tell some of these stories
because it is the stuff that kind of
conveniently that gets left out of TED
Talks later. Do you know what I mean?
>> Well, I am, yeah. I mean, actually the
origin stories for founders is always
like, "Ever since Sarah was 3 years old,
she dreamed of starting an accounting
software firm." You know, you're like,
"Come on." Do you know what I mean?
It's ridiculous. And so, a lot of the
stories that are told about founders are
very revisionist, and they make it the
life's passion of this You know, it
sometimes it really is, but you're like,
"No, when they were five, they did not,
you know,
>> [laughter]
>> collect things, and then that turned
into Pinterest 30 years later or
whatever." Like,
"They always dreamed of building AGI
when they were four, and that's why Sam
Altman started OpenAI or whatever." Mhm.
So, I think a lot of these things are
very kind of ridiculous in terms of how
they're written later.
And I think the product really, really
matters, and I think sometimes great
product just wins.
And the reason great product just wins
is that opens up a form of distribution
that didn't exist before, or people will
buy it despite the lack of distribution
or relationships for a company.
>> Mhm.
>> And the flip side of it is that the
companies that are really good have an
enormously good product engine.
And then they have an amazing
distribution engine.
And sometimes that distribution engine
is built into the product. That's like
Cursor or WinZip just distributing
through product-like growth, where
developers just find it and start using
it, and it helps them, and so they tell
other developers,
and it's pure word-of-mouth.
But often there's very aggressive sales,
marketing, other components to it.
>> Mhm.
>> And so, for example, when I was at
Google, they were spending hundreds of
millions of dollars a year, which at the
time was real money,
on distributing search, and they had
this little thing called the toolbar
that would like fit into a browser. Cuz
right now, browsers like with Chrome,
you type in
words or whatever, and then it instantly
searches it. Back then, the main
browsers were like Netscape and Internet
Explorer, etc.
And the browser bar thing didn't exist,
and they had this little client app that
you'd install, and they paid
basically every company on the internet
to cross-download it.
>> Mhm.
>> In other words, you're installing Adobe,
you're installing some malware detector
thing, you'd install and it would always
download the toolbar, cuz it they got
paid to distribute it, right? Mhm. very
aggressive distribution tactics. And to
your point, that was Facebook and
Facebook buying ads against people's
names in Europe. Can you explain that?
What are they doing? What was their end
game? They were basically trying to
create network liquidity in markets
where they were
earlier behind. And so, they would
basically buy ads of literally a
person's name, and one of the most
common queries is people searching
themselves.
And so, you'd be like, "Oh, let me look
up Tim Ferriss on Google or whatever."
And there'd be a Facebook ad saying,
"Hey, Tim Ferriss on Facebook." [__]
you'd click, and you'd land on the
sign-up flow for Facebook, right? This
was years ago.
This was TikTok and ByteDance, right? It
was basically they spent billions of
dollars
distributing TikTok so they could build
enough of a network to train AI
algorithms to start telling people what
to do, and also to get content creators
on. Where did they spend that money? On
distribution in this case of, say,
TikTok? My sense is it's ads again.
Yeah. You kind of see this over and over
again. I mean, for enterprise, Snowflake
spent billions of dollars on sales
people and compensation and channel
partnerships.
So, again, like distribution is really
important. Mhm. Every once in a while,
you see a company that actually wins not
because of product, but because they're
just better at sales and marketing and
distribution. And often, that's a bummer
for technologists such as myself, cuz
you're like, you know, the best product
should always win. Mhm. Sometimes it
does, but sometimes it's just who got
there early and developed a brand, or
who got ahead on distribution, you know?
I'm looking at a piece in front of me.
This is from a while ago, but
it's you discussing long-held dogma that
ends up being unviable. So, for
instance, the common-held belief after
PayPal sold to eBay that fraud will kill
you in the payment space, right?
And I'm wondering how you orient
yourself as an investor to
stress test
those types of dogma. It's really hard
because you often end up You start out
with some set of beliefs. You think
something's interesting.
Well, maybe you invest in it. Maybe you
start a company in it.
And then it turns out the thing you
think is really interesting turns out to
be really hard and you get killed.
And then 5 years later a company comes
up that actually does it and wins.
>> Mhm.
>> And
the question is why? Why did the thing
suddenly work when it didn't before? Or
there's 10 attempts to do X and then
suddenly is it the technology got good
enough? It could be a regulatory change.
It could be a market shift. It could be
whatever. An example that may be Harvey
and Legal where selling the law firm
traditionally has been awful.
And Harvey's not much broader than that,
right? They also have strong enterprise
adoption and
lots of different people using them in
different ways, but the dogma was always
like building stuff for law firms is
crappy as a business and you should
never do it. But what AI did is it
shifted things from selling tools to
selling work product or selling units of
labor. That's really the
shift in generative AI.
We're going from seats and we're going
from software
and SaaS and we're moving into a world
where we're selling human labor
equivalents. We're selling work hours or
labor hours or whatever you want to call
it.
>> Mhm.
>> cognition. And so Harvey is effectively
helping really augment lawyers in
different ways. And part of that's a
knowledge corpus, but a lot of it is
this tooling that really helps lawyers
achieve the goals that they have in
different ways in a collaborative manner
in some cases. And so this is a
fundamentally different type of product
from what people were selling before.
And so it opened up the market in a way
that the market wasn't open before.
There's actually a broader conversation
around is the world market limited or
founder limited in terms of
entrepreneurial success. The Y
Combinator school of thought is that we
just don't have enough founders and if
we had 10 times as many founders, we'd
have 10 times as many big companies.
And there's an alternate school of
thought which is how many markets are
actually open in any given moment in
time. And those are the ones where you
can build big companies cuz if the
market isn't open to innovation or
change or whatever or hasn't is
undergoing a shift, you can't really
build anything there anyhow, so why do
it? And the striking thing about AI is
it's opened up tons and tons of markets
that were closed for a long time.
And it's opened it up because of
capabilities, but it's also opened it up
because every CEO is asking themselves,
"What's my AI story?"
And there's way more openness to try
things than I've ever seen in my life.
And so,
we have this odd moment in time where
things are massively available for
founders to do new things.
And if you're an AI company and you're
not seeing explosive growth quickly,
something's fundamentally broken.
Because the markets are so open
that you can suddenly grow at a rate
that you've never grown before. There's
always been cases of companies that just
go like this.
But again, you look at the ramps of
OpenAI and Anthropic, and it's the
fastest ramps to tens of billions ever.
Percentages of GDP, it's like crazy.
>> If we come back to your comment of
not necessarily market first and
strength of team second all the time,
but like you said, you 90% agree with
that, right? And
if you have an excellent team in a
terrible market, like that's going to be
that's going to be a difficult one to
execute. How do you determine what is a
good versus great market, or just what
is a great market? What do you look for?
And the example you gave, I might be
overreading this, but what you said that
when Google shut down, I think it was
Maven, right? That's an interesting kind
of event-based approach as an input to
investing, right? Cuz you're like,
"Okay, if they're not going to build it,
>> We're really
>> that suddenly creates
a playing field for
startups.
>> Yeah.
>> To play in that space. So, could you
speak to more
of how you determine or look for great
markets?
>> I mean, there's a few different ways to
think about it. One is like, some people
take the framework of why now? What's
shifted now that makes it suddenly an
interesting market because people have
been trying to do things for a long time
in every market. And so, that may be a
regulatory shift, right? Samsara, the
fleet management company benefited from
the fact that suddenly there's
regulation around needing in-cab
monitoring of drivers. So, you had
suddenly cameras watching people so they
don't fall asleep while they're driving
trucks on the road, right? And so, that
was their entry point to then start
building out a suite of the
But it was a regulatory shift. Sometimes
there's technology shifts like what's
happening in AI and the crazy thing
about that AI shift is
the foundation models instantly plugged
into a massive set of markets which is
basically all enterprise data and
information and email and just
all white collar work was suddenly
available to AI cuz it's a perfect
technology for that. It also plugged
into code which is a type of white
collar work. So it's just suddenly it
just inserts into language and language
is used everywhere in in enterprises as
well as in consumer and so there's just
a massive market to tap into and
transform or set of markets. Robotics is
a little bit different from that because
even if you had the world's best robotic
model the sub markets that already have
robotic hardware are quite small on a
relative basis.
And so you don't have that instant
runway that you would with
language unless you come up with
something new there. That's kind of an
aside but I think robotics is really
interesting and will be important. It's
more just that nuance of like what's
that instant thing you plug into
commercially? And then
there's regulatory shifts there's
technology shifts there's
incumbency or company shifts competitive
shifts.
A company may blow itself up and may get
bought by a competitor. One company I'm
I'm excited about on the security side
is called Infracloud and they're
basically competing in part with Hashi.
Hashi got bought by IBM. Anytime you get
bought by IBM you slow you slow down a
lot usually.
>> Mhm.
>> Suddenly it creates more opportunity for
a startup. So I just feel like there are
these different things that can change
in a given moment in time.
>> Mhm.
>> It could be the market growing really
fast. That's Coinbase in crypto, right?
You just have suddenly this adoption and
proliferation of token types. There's
lots and lots and lots of different
markets that are interesting. The
commonality is usually like is it also
big? Is there a big enough TAM? And
there's two types of TAMs. There's fake
TAM.
>> Just for people listening who might not
have it. Yeah, total addressable market.
>> Total addressable market. So what's the
market you're in?
And sometimes people come up with these
fake markets. They're like, "Oh well
we are facilitating
global e-commerce and global e-commerce
I'm making up the number is $30 a year
and so we're in a $30 a year market and
if we get just a 10th of a percent of
that, it's 300 billion of revenue, and
you're like, that's not
that's not your market. Your market is
like you built this little optimization
engine for SMB websites or whatever.
That's not a $30 trillion
market. And so, really it's kind of
defining the market. There's a really
famous example of this where defining
your market changes how you think about
it.
And so, that was Coca-Cola, right? So,
Coke and Pepsi were roughly neck and
neck in terms of market share
for decades.
And then, one of the Coke CEOs said,
"Hey,
maybe we should be thinking about our
share as share of
liquid sold.
Like drinks, not share of soda.
And so, we just went from 50% market
share to 0.5%.
And that's why they bought Dasani, and
that's why they entered all these other
markets, right? Because they said,
"Our definition of our market is wrong.
We're not in the soda pop business,
we're in the drinks business." And so, I
think also sometimes reconceptualizing
what you're doing can really help change
your scope of ambition or how you think
about what you're doing.
>> If you're trying to spot
along the lines of the fraud will kill
you in the payment space, right? Any
dogma in the AI world, the sphere of AI,
right?
Anything Anything hop to mind where you
think, "Uh, maybe that's not true now,
or maybe in like 2 years it'll be
completely untrue, but people will have
latched onto this belief as
one of the thou shalt not or thou thou
shalt
commandments?
>> I don't know. I mean, there's some
things that have circulated in the past
around what's the ROI on the CapEx spend
of the and will it ever be paid back?
And I just like,
I think that stuff is probably off. But
yeah, I think fundamentally, there are
moments in time where it's very smart to
be contrarian. And there are moments in
time where being consensus is the
smartest possible thing you can do. And
I think right now we're in a moment in
time where being consensus is very
right.
You know, and you can really overthink
it, and what's the contrarian thing? We
should go do a bunch of hardware stuff
cuz blah blah blah.
And you're like, maybe I should just buy
more AI. You know what I mean? I think
people make these things way too
complicated.
>> Oh, yeah, true in every aspect of life,
probably. Let's just say you were
mentoring. This is somebody you really
care about, right?
We can make up an avatar, whatever. Like
>> [laughter]
>> nephew of one of your best friends, or
son of one of your best friends, or
daughter, who's really smart, got an
engineering degree, came out of MIT, has
a couple of
hits in angel investing, and they're
like, all right, I think I'm going to
raise a fund.
>> Mhm.
>> They don't have the access necessarily
that you do to AI, let's just say.
Are there any things categorically you
would say would be on the do not invest
list because they're likely to be
annihilated
or consumed or replicated by AI?
>> [clears throat]
>> I think the reality is that when people
start off as investors,
a lot of the times the reason they have
early-stage funds is because you can
always get access to the early stages of
companies if you just start helping
people.
>> Mhm.
>> I mean, that's kind of what I did
accidentally, but the reality is I've
seen that over and over.
You fall in with the right group of
people cuz the smartest people also
aggregate together, and you start
helping people out, and they just ask if
you want to invest, and you start
investing, and suddenly you have a great
track record, and you raise bigger
funds, and then you go later stage cuz
that same cohort has grown up, and
they've started doing later stuff, and
>> Mhm.
>> when somebody can get access to
everything else. That's kind of the
traditional venture story, and it has
been, I think, for decades in some
sense. So, I think that's still very
tenable, and you can still do it for AI.
You can do it for anything. I don't
think you have to go off and do like
energy investing or something.
>> You have mentioned in the past a key
learning, [snorts]
maybe that's an overstatement, but you
can correct me, from Vinod Khosla.
And [snorts]
I think the wording is along the lines
of your market entry strategy is off, is
it different from your market disruption
strategy? Yeah. Could you speak to that?
>> There's sort of two or three versions of
this. Version one is you do something
that's really weird and it starts off
looking like a toy and then it turns out
to be really important. And that would
be Instagram or Twitter or some of these
more social products, right? Where
the initial use case is very different
from how it's used today and it kind of
evolved as a product and how people
perceive it and use it. And that's one
version of it and that's usually more
consumer-centric. Another version of
that would be SpaceX and Starlink where
they started off with launch and getting
things up into space and they realized,
"Hey, they have a cost advantage for
satellites." And then they built out the
Starlink network, which is now like a
major driver of their business, right?
And so, what they did expanded a lot and
kind of shifted in terms of their market
entry with space launch, their
disruption is Starlink in some sense.
So, I do think there's lots of examples
like that over time.
>> Coming back to information and just
consumption,
>> [laughter]
>> how do you consume most of your
information? Like, what would the pie
chart break down to in terms of
if you listens to podcasts versus books
versus X versus white papers versus
something else?
>> I think a lot of what I've done is
collapsed into three things. It's X,
it's reading some technical paper /
journals in some cases if it's more of
the biology side. A lot of it I do
biology investing. It's like a
But, you know, papers. Although, the
papers in the AI industry have really
dropped off given the competitive nature
of everything now.
>> Mhm.
>> And then talking to people. I found that
like 20 minutes with somebody really
smart on a topic
gives me more information and insights
and leads on what to go read about than
doing some exhaustive research.
Actually, the fourth thing is now using
models to do research for me.
>> Mhm. [clears throat]
>> That could be OpenAI, that could be
Claude, that could be Perplexity, that
could be Gemini. But, and for each of
them I actually use different things or
I do different things with each of them.
>> What do you do with the different
models?
>> I'll just give you one example versus go
through every single one of them, but
>> Sure.
>> Gemini I actually feel like if I'm
looking up more like activities, like
hey I'm planning a trip somewhere.
I actually feel like the Google corpus
and all the stuff they built over time
is quite useful for like travel tips of
certain types.
>> Mhm.
>> And so that'd be a Gemini specific
thing. That doesn't mean the other
models can't do it well. It's more just
like I've I've tended to get more
accurate like rankings of things that
way.
>> Mhm.
>> And I'll ask for like breakdowns and
rankings across multiple dimensions and
all the stuff
for scoring of things. I did like a deep
dive in a few different areas of ADHD
and ASD.
>> What's ASD?
>> Oh, I'm sorry. It's autism spectrum.
>> I see. I got it. Mhm.
>> So basically like if you look at autism,
it went from I'm going to misquote the
numbers, so you know, I should look
these up better. But I think it's
something like one in a few thousand of
the population was diagnosed with autism
like 30 years ago, 40 years ago. And now
it's like 3%.
>> Mhm.
>> So you're like, well, what is that? Is
that change in older parents having more
kids, which it turns out that that's not
the driver. Is it
some shift in the environment? Is it It
turns out that it's just diagnostic
criteria has shifted.
>> Ah.
>> And [clears throat] there's a lot of
incentives to actually diagnose people
in the schools. That's roughly the
summary of why we have so many kids that
are classified as either having
attention deficit
where there's also like a financial
incentive for doctors to do it cuz they
can prescribe drugs
>> Mhm.
>> versus autism, but both have gone up
dramatically in terms of diagnoses,
right? And
it's unclear to me that more people
actually have it.
>> Mhm.
>> It's just diagnosed dramatically more
broadly.
>> Which model were you investigating that
with?
>> Usually when I do things like that, I
use two or three models at once and then
I ask for primary literature and then
ask for summary charts. And actually
have this whole breakdown of like stuff
that I ask for each output so that I can
go back and double-check the data.
>> Mhm.
>> And then reread through the literature
and everything else. And there's really
interesting things that came out of the
autism one in particular because it
turned out maternal age actually has a
bigger impact than paternal age
>> Mhm.
>> in some of the studies. And people
always talk about paternal age.
>> Mhm.
>> And then you're like, well, why are
people only talking about paternal age?
Is there a societal incentive for that?
Is it a political belief system? Like
why is that the point of emphasis?
>> Mhm.
>> Which I thought was really interesting,
right?
>> Mhm.
>> So there's other things that kind of
come out of that in terms of questions,
in terms of the why of things.
>> But why were you looking into that
specifically?
>> I thought it was interesting.
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. Seems like it's gone up a lot. Let
me try and understand why.
>> Mhm.
>> And so I started looking into it.
>> I was also talking to a friend of mine
who is in her sort of mid to late 30s.
And she was dating a guy who was in his
late 40s, early 50s, and she brought up
oh, she was worried about
autism and what would happen with them
if they had kids and all the stuff.
And so then I did this deep dive as part
of that, too.
>> Mhm.
>> And the takeaway was I can't remember
exactly what it was. I'm making it up,
so please don't quote me on this. I can
look it up later, but it was like
there's a 10% increase for every 5 to 10
years incremental paternal and maternal
age, and again, maternal was actually a
little bit stronger in some of the data
sets. And the thing is, though, if you
believe that it's one in 5,000 or one in
whatever in the population,
that 10%, 20% difference doesn't matter.
>> Mhm.
>> Right? From a population frequency
perspective, it's just diagnostic
criteria went way up.
>> That's it's true for a lot a lot of
diagnoses.
>> A lot of stuff, but like societally
we're told oh, it's like the age of the
parents is driving all these autism
rates up, and you're like, no, it's like
all these incentives, and then you look
at some of the school systems, it's like
60% of all the autism diagnoses in I
think it was the state of New Jersey or
something
were
not actually based on any clinical
criteria. It's just a teacher randomly
saying this person has autism.
>> Oh god, terrible.
>> Right? And [snorts] so you start digging
into these things and you're like, wow,
this is super interesting, and these
models are really valuable and helpful
for that. So I've been doing a lot of
back to your question of where do I get
information. Part of it has been these
deep dives with models into like
questions that I just find interesting
where
I ask them to aggregate clinical trial
data or aggregate different types of
information, and then give me the
primary sources, and then give me
summaries and
double check things and so I have like a
whole series of prompts around that to
kind of also clean data and check it and
that's really fun. And then I always set
it up in multiple models and just see
like what they each come up with.
>> When you talk to people and this may be
too much of a kind of
amorphous topic for us to dive into in a
meaningful way, but let's just say
you find somebody you want to talk to
for 20 minutes. How do you typically
find those people? I suspect there are a
lot of ways, but are you finding them on
X versus finding them in a technical
paper versus finding them somewhere
else? Just to get an idea. And then when
you get on the phone with such a person
are there repeating trains of
questioning or certain ways that you
like to approach it?
>> I think there's three different types of
things. One is
hey, I'm doing a deep dive in an area
just cuz I think it's interesting or
maybe it's relevant to like an area I
want to invest in. Often honestly just
is it interesting?
And then I'll try to quickly triangulate
for the smartest people on the thing and
that may technical papers, that may just
be asking each person I talk to who's
really smart. There's one form of that
which is hey, it's very informational
and I'm trying to do a deep dive on
something. I mean I work with some of
the early AI researchers at Google.
That's how I knew like Noam Shazeer who
started Character and then went back to
Google and that's how I met a bunch of
other folks, but some of the people I
just met, you know, just interesting
paper, let me look them up or hey,
everybody says this person's really
smart, let me talk to them. That's one
form. A second form is I do think like
really smart people tend to aggregate
and so if you're just hanging out with
smart people, you keep meeting other
smart people.
>> Mhm.
>> And people who are polymathic tend to
hang out with people who are polymathic
and it's kind of like like attracts like
for all sorts of things. So that's sort
of a second set. These are probably the
two main things. I mean sometimes people
also just refer people over to me.
They'll say hey, I think you two would
like chatting.
>> Mhm.
>> There's a separate thing which is
there's people that I go back to
recurrently, right? Which is more like I
think this is one of the smartest people
about where AI is heading. Let me talk
to them all the time or
this is one of the smartest people about
longevity. Like Kristen, the CEO of I
call sometimes about random
longevity-related things because she
knows so much about every topic in it.
She's very thoughtful. She's very
willing to question her own assumptions.
It's very just like
truth-seeking in a way that most people
aren't. And people always use that term,
but she really is just like, "What's
correct? Let me just figure it out."
She's like a PhD and postdoc in like
bioinformatics and aging. She's super
legit. And so, that's an example of
somebody that I'll call for like
longevity stuff.
So, I just have certain people I'll call
for certain topics.
>> So, you have literacies.
It's kind of quaint how, you know, I
went to the first Quantified Self meet
up in
whatever it was, 2008 or something, with
12 people sitting around in Kevin
Kelly's house talking about
measuring things with Excel
spreadsheets. The world has changed. So,
there are armies of tens of thousands of
self-described biohackers and so on
talking about longevity. There's a lot
of nonsense. For yourself, personally,
where have you landed in terms of
interventions or thinking about
interventions
for yourself?
>> I haven't done a ton. You know, it feels
like a lot collapses into like sleep
well, exercise a lot, you know, etc.
Like there's a handful of things that
kind of matter. Eat well.
And so, I've kind of collapsed on all
that stuff. I think there's one or two
things that maybe you can take that are
helpful. And then, there's some things I
always thought it'd be fun to experiment
with that I haven't done yet.
>> Like what?
>> I thought it'd be cool to try like a
rapamycin pulse or something.
So, stuff like that. But, the reality is
that I'm kind of waiting for the real
drugs to come out. And then, maybe I'd
use those. Some of the ones that
actually think will really impinge on
longevity or certain systems. Like we
were talking earlier about, as you age,
the muscle that holds the lens of your
eye weakens. And that's part of the
reason that your ability to focus kind
of gets screwed up. And so,
there should be eye drops for that. Like
there's a bunch of stuff around
neurosensory aging that I'd love to fund
a startup.
>> Mhm.
>> There's a bunch of stuff around the
cosmetics of aging that I've long been
talking about trying to find I actually
funded a clinical trial at Stanford to
to work on that, for example.
>> Mhm.
>> Cuz I think it's very interesting. And
peptides to me is basically that.
I think a lot of those people are taking
peptides as like certain forms of
health, but also certain forms of
cosmetic applications like 5-HKCU and
melanotan and all these things are
basically cosmetic in nature.
>> You mentioned a handful of things that
seem helpful to take. Are those just the
big [laughter]
you know, vitamin D or are we talking
about other things? What are what are
more on that short list?
>> Vitamin D and creatine.
>> Yeah.
>> Got it.
>> If you want to lift. I don't know what's
on your list. I mean, you've thought
about this so much more than I have.
What are you taking or what are you
thinking about or
>> I'm much more conservative than I think
people would expect. You know, I've
played around with a lot of things in my
earlier days and a lot of it is very, I
would say, capped risk if you're
experimenting as I was with first
generation Dexcom continuous glucose
monitors in 2008, right? They were were
2009, very unpleasant to wear.
>> Yeah.
>> And I wasn't aware of any non-type 1
diabetics using them at the time. But I
wasn't using much in terms of
let's [snorts] just say questionable
gene therapy, flying to other countries
to
use something like a follistatin. Not to
throw it under the bus, but I feel like
the general heuristic of no biological
free lunch, I recognize it's very
simplistic, but it's pretty helpful. At
least it will aid you in avoiding a lot
of pitfalls, right? So, I mean, there
are things I'm experimenting with.
Different forms of ketone esters and
salts, for instance. I think some could
be very, very interesting for
cerebral vasculature. And since I have
Alzheimer's disease, Parkinson's, etc.
in my family, including for people who
are APOE33, so there are certainly many
other risk factors. I'm paying a lot of
attention to that side of things, you
know, obeticholic acid, I think, is one
to keep an eye on. That's not yet ready
for primetime, but rapamycin is
interesting. I do think rapamycin is
interesting with a lot of asterisks
because you can screw yourself up if you
don't know what you're doing.
And
if you're playing with any
immunosuppressant, I mean, you just have
to be very careful,
but
looking at combining that, for instance,
one of the experiments that I might do
is and I would have a cleaner read of
signal if I only did one intervention,
but real life is different from
Yeah. Waiting for
>> [laughter]
>> science sometimes.
>> Revert
>> So, possibly combining Norwegian 4 by 4
interval training with rapamycin pulsing
to look at volumetric changes, if any,
in the hippocampus and other areas.
Like, I think that's a pretty
interesting
hypothesis we're testing.
But otherwise, it's basic basic, right?
It's creatine, it's the vitamin D's.
Look, if you have methylation issues or
you're taking medication, as I am, like
omeprazole, which can inhibit magnesium
absorption and other things, like you
want to keep an eye on that, but not too
fancy, you know, I think urolithin A is
pretty interesting.
>> [clears throat]
>> The data keeps mounting on that. I do
have a keen interest in mitochondrial
health. So, if there are things, which
could also include
regular intermittent fasting and
occasional 3 to 7-day fasting, which
could be a fast-mimicking diet, most
recently for me, based on the input from
Dr. Dominic D'Agostino, trying to foster
autophagy and mitophagy with some
regularity, not all the time. Sure. I'm
not trying to optimize for that all the
time.
>> One thing I've been wondering, so if you
look at like a computer
and often the key to fixing your laptop
or the key to fixing any system is you
just [__] reboot it, right?
>> Yeah.
>> You reload the system and it just works
magically. Is there like a equivalent of
that? Is it like going under for
anesthesia?
Is there some nerve freezing thing that
some people have been doing recently?
>> Oof. Yeah, I don't know.
Sounds scary. Oh, maybe stellate
ganglion block?
>> Yeah, that's it. The stellate ganglion
block.
>> Yeah. Yeah, I mean the rebooting
Oh, man. I'm like letting out an exhale
because
I there are some interesting options for
very specific use cases. It makes sense
conceptually. I mean, you're more
qualified to speak to this, but I would
say just spending a lot of time around
neuroscientists and I I spend a lot of
my time in terms of information intake
reading
or doing my best. Fortunately with AI
tools, it's become a lot easier. Not
just getting a synopsis, but actually
using it to help you
learn concepts that you can kind of
layer in some
rational sequence. Sure. But, I read a
lot of neuroscience stuff and a lot of
optical stuff. There's actually a
surprising amount of I mean, there's
maybe not so surprising like
very strong intersection there. So, if
you're looking at like PBM and like
photobiomodulation through the eyes, I
mean, you can do it transcranially as
well. I would give a note of caution for
that for folks, but the reboot side I
would say for instance, and people have
experienced this to a lesser extent with
GLP-1 agonists. If they take it for
weight loss, maybe they stop smoking or
they cut back on drinking or
they have these
kind of system-wide decreases or
increases in it in impulse control.
>> Yeah.
>> For someone who's saying opiate addict,
I think that ibogaine, which
in the future may take the form of an
active metabolite or something like
that,
in flood dosing,
at least that's seems pretty necessary
at this point, relatively high doses,
under medical supervision cuz you can
have fatal cardiac events.
Co-administration of magnesium seems to
help, but it's dangerous stuff. People
should be careful.
You can and there are lots of people
historically who deserve a lot of credit
for this, like Howard Lotsof
and his wife, but
opiate addicts can go through
flood dosing of Ibogaine and come out
and they're basically given a window
with which they
won't experience withdrawal symptoms,
physical withdrawal symptoms.
And I think there probably applications
to other things with Ibogaine or
pharmacological interventions like
Ibogaine. And some of the craziest
stuff, honestly, related to that
molecule is
the
and I'm skeptical of this simple
description, but there's a reversal in
brain age. It's it changes in the brain
based on MRIs. Nolan Williams, rest in
peace, and his lab looked at this pretty
closely, pre- and post-dosing of
Ibogaine for veterans with traumatic
brain injury. And some of that might be
due to something called glial derived
neurotrophic factor, right? People might
be familiar with like BDNF.
So, Ibogaine is one interesting option.
Anesthesia, I've become a lot more
cautious with general anesthesia.
>> Yeah.
>> Like I just had surgery yesterday and I
opted for local anesthesia, which in
this case was not a big deal cuz it was
just you can see it, like had something
cut out of my head,
but
coming back to the
and I'm going to riff for a second here,
but the
autism spectrum disorder and ADHD
example you were unpacking where you
talked about the incentives, they might
be in perverse incentives to diagnose.
Well,
I mean,
not to quote Munger, right? But it's
like follow the money, right?
>> [laughter]
>> And a lot of people are put under
general who really don't need to be put
under general, but it adds a very, very,
very huge
line item to the tab.
And there are people
who go under anesthesia and wake up and
do not retain
the same ability to recall memories and
so on. Like their personalities become
in some way destabilized. And the fact
of the matter is
that a lot of anesthesia is very poorly
understood. We know it works, but it's
very poorly understood. And I don't
think
a lot of people
realize because why would they unless
they've
you know, just spending a lot of time
looking into this. There are lots of
medications that are incredibly
well-known, commonly prescribed for
which the mechanisms of action are
really poorly understood, if they're
understood at all. You know, like we
know based on studies they appear to be
well tolerated. Like side effects
profiles include A through Z.
And it certainly seems to exert this
effect or have an impact on biomarker X,
but we don't actually [__] know how
it works, you know? And there's just a
lot of stuff that falls into that
bucket. And so I am cautious with a lot
of it. But to come back to your
question, I went off on a bit of a TED
Talk. The most interesting reboot that
I've seen and I don't I don't want to
really water it down to like the
dopaminergic system cuz there's a lot
more to it, but I began I think more so
than I began itself shows what is
possible and I don't know if that's
limited to drugs. I am very bullish and
there going to be fuck-ups, there going
to be some sidebars that don't look so
good. But brain stimulation and
bioelectric medicine
broadly speaking
is one of the great next frontiers,
certainly in treating what we might
consider psychiatric disorders.
But also for performance enhancement and
we're at a point kind of looking for
those external why now answers, right?
There are actually some really good
answers to why now for this is a field.
And
I think people will be experimenting a
lot with this but without the use of
pills and potions and IVs and actually
non-invasive brain stimulation, maybe
some invasive in the case of implants.
So that's a long answer, but yeah,
that's on what I'm thinking about and
tracking. I mean some of this stuff
we'll see, but I think a lot of this
stuff could be outpatient procedure. You
walk in, you're in there for an hour or
two and then you're out.
So we'll see. Let me ask just a couple
of last questions and then if there's
anything else we want to bat around we
can bat it around, but I appreciate the
time.
A lot of 5 years from now is looking
back at a lot of today.
>> Yeah.
>> Are there any beliefs, positions, could
be related to AI or otherwise that you
think are more likely than others to be
wrong?
>> Hmm, that's a good question. I think
there's all sorts of things I'm going to
get wrong. I mean I think we're living
through a period of big changes means
big uncertainty and so
I wouldn't be surprised if half the
things I think are going to happen don't
or happen even more so or whatever it
may be. And that's part of the fun of it
in terms of if we had a perfectly
predictive future it'd be very boring,
right? Because we we'd know exactly
what's going to happen and it'd be
awful.
Ties into notions of free will and all
sorts of other things, right? I'm sure
there's a lot. I think there's a
separate question of just one exercise
I've been going through recently is and
I've never done this before, you know a
lot of what you do in life it's back the
John Lennon quote, life is what happens
you're making other plans.
For the first time I'm actually thinking
like what's my 10-year plan, right?
Across a few different dimensions of
life.
And the basic question is
I won't get it right, right? I can try
and have a plan for 10 years. Of course
it's not going to be what I think. But
it's more does it change the scope of
ambition
that you have? Does it change how you
think about life? And so I've been
trying to think in those terms, like
what do I want to do over the next
decade?
And that what does that mean in terms of
the near term what I do in order to get
there in 10 years? And so I think that's
been very
eye-opening for me in terms of shifting
some of my mindset around what I should
be trying or not trying to do. Now,
the AGI killed people will say, well, in
two years we have AGI so it doesn't
matter what your plans are.
But I find that to be a very kind of
defeatist view of the world, you know,
it's like I'm going to give up because I
was
versus saying great, I'm going to have
this plan and I can adjust it as needed,
but through this time of change there'll
be some really interesting things for me
to do in the world.
>> Elad, do you have anything else you'd
like to say, comments, requests for the
audience, thanks to point people to
anything at all before we
wind to a close. People can find you on
X at Elad Gil, eladgil.com, certainly
the Substack blog, blog.eladgil.com,
and elsewhere. We'll link everything in
the show notes, but anything else that
you'd like to add?
>> Yeah, it was nice to chat with you as
always. I really enjoyed it, so thanks
for having me on.
>> Yeah, thanks, man. Always a pleasure.
And to everybody listening or watching,
we will link everything in the show
notes, tim.blog/podcast,
and until next time, as always, be a bit
kinder than is necessary to others, but
also to yourself. Thanks for tuning in.